The Papers of Georg and Max Bredig
Science History Institute
- Series III: Publications, III
  - Series III, Sub-Series II: Books
    - Jorissen, Willem P, and L T. Reicher. J.H. Van't Hoffs Amsterdamer Periode 1877-1895. Helder, Holland: De Boer
      Books volume 62
    - Haas, Arthur E. Materiewellen Und Quantenmechanik: E. Einf. Auf Grund D. Theorien Von De Broglie, Schroedinger, Heisenberg U. Dirac. Leipzig: Akad. Verl. -Ges
      Books volume 49
    - Avogadro, Amedeo, and Icilio Guareschi. Opere Scelte Di Amedeo Avogadro: Pubblicate Dalla R. Accademia Delle Scienze di Torino. Torino: Unione tipografico-editrice torinese
      Books volume 6
    - Hoff, J.H. Vorlesungen Über Theoretische Und Physikalische Chemie: 3. Heft. Braunschweig: Vieweg
      Books volume 56
    - Lorentz, Hendrik A, and Adriaan D. Fokker. Vorlesungen Über Theoretische Physik an Der Universität Leiden: 1. Leipzig: Akad. Verl. -Ges
      Books volume 72
    - Lindh, Axel E. Rontgenspektroskopie. Leipzig: Akademische
      Books volume 70
    - Curie, Pierre. Traite De Radioactivite Tome I. Paris: Gauthier-Villars
      Books volume 27
    - Kopp, Hermann. Aus Der Molecular-Welt. Heidelberg: Winter
      Books volume 65
    - Goldschmidt, Stefan. Stereochemie. Leipzig: Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft
      Books volume 45
    - Frey, Albert, and Hermann Ambronn. Das Polarisationsmikroskop: Seine Anwendung in Der Kolloid- Forschung Und in Der Färberei: Von Hermann Ambronn Und Albert Frey. Lpz
      Books volume 43
    - Arrhenius, Svante. Die Chemie Und des Modern Leben. Leipzig
      Books volume 3
    - "Ostwald's Klassiker der Exakten Wissenschaften." Leipzig (numbers: 1, 3-4, 8, 13, 15-17, 20-40, 42, 44-45, 52-53, 56, 58, 66, 68-70, 72, 74-76, 79-81, 86, 88, 90, 92, 94, 96-101, 104, 106, 110, 118, 121, 124-126, 128, 132, 137, 139, 148, 150, 152, 157, 160, 163, 173-174, 179, 188, 193, 196, 199, 200, 204, 207)
      Books volume 96-186
    - Tammann, Gustav. Kristallisieren Und Schmelzen: Ein Beitrag Zur Lehre der Änderungen des Aggregatzustandes. Leipzig: Barth
      Books volume 206
    - Kuhn, Werner. Physikalische Chemie. Leipzig: Quelle und Meyer
      Books volume 67
    - Dede, L. Komplexchemie: Einführung in die Chemie der Komplexen Verbindungen. Berlin: Walter de Gruyter
      Books volume 30
    - Lao-tse, Laozi, and Richard Wilhelm. Laotse Tao Te King: Das Buch des Alten Vom Sinn Und Leben. Jena: Diederich
      Books volume 68
    - Ostwald, Wilhelm. Die Farbschule: Eine Anleitung Zur Praktischen Erlernung der Wissenschaftlichen Farbenlehre: Mit 6 Tafeln Und 11 Figuren Im Text. Leipzig: Verl. Unesma
      Books volume 90
    - Ostwald, Wilhelm, and J H. Hoff. Zeitschrift Für Physikalische Chemie, Band 137-138. Leipzig: Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft
      Books volume 95
    - Jaeger, Francis M. Eine Anleitung Zur Ausführung Exakter Physiko-Chemischer Messungen Bei Höheren Temperaturen: Mit Besonderer Berücksichtigung des Studiums der Mineralsynthese Und der Silikatchemie. Groningen: J.B. Wolters' u.m
      Books volume 59
    - Schenck, Rudolf. Physikalische Chemie der Metalle: 6 Vorträge Über Die Wissenschaftlichen Grundlagen der Metallurgie; Mit 114 Abb. Halle a. S: Knapp
      Books volume 200
    - Bruhns, Wilhelm. Petrographie: (gesteinskunde). Leipzig: Göschen
      Books volume 19
    - Cohen, Ernst. Physikalisch-chemische Metamorphose Und Einige Piezochemische Probleme. Leipzig: Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft MbH, Leipzig
      Books volume 25
    - Ostwald, Grete. Wilhelm Ostwald, Mein Vater. Stuttgart
      Books volume 84
    - Nernst, Walther, and A Schoenflies. Einführung in die Mathematische Behandlung der Naturwissenschaften: Kurzgefasstes Lehrbuch der Differential Und Integralrechnung Mit Besonderer Berüchsichtigung der Chemie. München: R. Oldenbourg
      Books volume 80
    - Curie, Pierre. Traite De Radioactivite Tome II. Paris: Gauthier-Villars
      Books volume 28
    - Kirchner, Fritz. Allgemeine Physik Der Röntgenstrahlen. Leipzig: Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft M.B.H
      Books volume 64
    - Nernst, Walther. Experimental and Theoretical Applications of Thermodynamics to Chemistry. London: Constable
      Books volume 79
    - Haas, Arthur E. Materiewellen Und Quantenmechanik: Eine Einführung Auf Grund der Theorien von De Broglie, Schrödinger Heisenberg Und Dirac. Leipzig: Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft
      Books volume 50
    - Becker, Hugo. Geometrisches Zeichnen. Leipzig: G.J. Göschen'sche Verlagshandlung
      Books volume 7
    - Cohen, Ernst. Jacobus Henricus Van't Hoff: Sein Leben Und Wirken. Leipzig: Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft m. b. h (autographed)
      Books volume 23
    - Bruhns, W. Kristallographie. Berlin
      Books volume 20
    - Bredig, Georg. Anorganische Fermente: Darstellung Kolloidaler Metalle Auf Elektrischem Wege Und Untersuchung Ihrer Katalytischen Eigenschaften; Kontaktchemische Studie. Leipzig: Engelmann (3 copies)
      Books volume 13
    - Ulich, Hermann. Chemische Thermodynamik: Einf. in D. Lehre Von D. Chem. Affinitaeten U. Gleichgewichten. Dresden
      Books volume 209
    - Ostwald, Wilhelm. Lebenslinien, Eine Selbstbiographie, T. 3.
      Books volume 94
    - Waals, Johannes D. Die Continuität des Gasförmigen Und Flüssigen Zustandes: 1. Leipzig: Barth
      Books volume 210
    - Jaeger, Francis M. Lectures on the Principle of Symmetry and Its Applications in All-Natural Sciences
      Books volume 58
    - Ihering, Albrecht. Maschinenkunde Für Chemiker. Leipzig: Barth
      Books volume 57
    - Haber, Fritz. Thermodynamik Technischer Gasreaktionen. München & Berlin: R. Oldenbourg
      Books volume 51
    - Moszkowski, Alexander. Einstein: Einblicke in Seine Gedankenwelt; Gemeinverständliche Betrachtungen Über Die Relativitätstheorie Und Ein Neues Weltsystem. Berlin: Fontane & Co
      Books volume 78
    - Ephraim, Fritz. Chemische Valenz Und Bindungslehre. Leipzig: Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft
      Books volume 36
    - Sieveking, Hermann. Einführung in Das Physikalische Praktikum.
      Books volume 202
    - Fodor, Stephan von. Edison: Der Lebensweg Eines Erfinders.
      Books volume 41
    - Roth, Walter and Karl Scheel. Landolt-börnstein Physikalisch-Chemische Tabellen, Dritter Erganzungsband II, Berlin: Verlag von Julius Springer
      Books volume 196
    - Ostwald, Wilhelm. Lebenslinien, Eine Selbstbiographie, T. 2.
      Books volume 93
    - Kühn, Alfred. Wörterbuch Der Kolloidchemie. Dresden: T. Steinkopff
      Books volume 66
    - Waals, Johannes D. Die Continuität des Gasförmigen Und Flüssigen Zustandes: 2. Leipzig: Barth
      Books volume 211
    - Lorentz, Hendrik A, and Gerhard C. Schmidt. Lehrbuch Der Differential Und Integralrechnung: Nebst Einer Einführung in Andere Teile der Mathematik; Mit 122 Fig. Leipzig: Barth
      Books volume 71
    - Drude, Paul. Lehrbuch Der Optik. Berlin. Leipzig: S. Hirzel
      Books volume 33
    - Ostwald, Wilhelm. Die Wissenschaftlichen Grundlagen der Analytischen Chemie: Elementar Dargestellt. Leipzig: Engelmann (autographed)
      Books volume 85
    - Planck, Max. Das Weltbild der Neuen Physik. Leipzig: J.A. Barth
      Books volume 190
    - Berzelius, Joens J, and Friedrich Wöhler. Lehrbuch Der Chemie: Bd. 6. Dresden: Arnold
      Books volume 9
    - Planck, Max. Vorlesungen Über Die Theorie der Wärmestrahlung: Mit 6 Abb. Leipzig: Barth
      Books volume 187
    - Abegg, Richard W. H. Die Theorie der Elektrolytischen Dissociation. Stuttgart: F. Enke
      Books volume 1
    - Mecklenburg, Werner. Kurzes Lehrbuch der Chemie.
      Books volume 76
    - Goerens, Paul. Einführung in Die Metallographie von Paul Goerens. Halle a.S: W. Knapp
      Books volume 44
    - Arrhenius, Svante, and Alexis Finkelstein. Theorien Der Chemie. Mit Unterstützung des Verfassers Aus Dem Englischen Manuskript Übersetzt von Alexis Finkelstein. Zweite Neubearbeitete Und Bedeutend Vermehrte Auflage. Leipzig
      Books volume 2
    - Auerbach, Felix. Die Methoden der Theoretischen Physik, Von Felix Auerbach. Leipzig: Akademische Verlagsgesellschaft
      Books volume 5
    - Cohen, Ernst. Physico-chemical Metamorphosis and Some Problems in Piezochemistry. New York, London: McGraw-Hill (autographed)
      Books volume 24
    - Fokker, A D, and H A. Lorentz. Vorlesungen Über Theoretische Physik an Der Universität Leiden: Kinetische Probleme: 3. Aethertheorien Und Aethermodelle.
      Books volume 42
    - Hoff, J. H. Vorlesungen Über Theoretische Und Physikalische Chemie. 1899. Braunschweig: Vieweg
      Books volume 55
    - Planck, Max. Vorlesungen Über Thermodynamik. Leipzig: Von Veit
      Books volume 189
    - Pohl, Robert W, and Klaus Lüders. Einführung in Die Physik: 2. Berlin: Springer
      Books volume 191
    - Ostwald, Wilhelm. Einführung in Die Farbenlehre. Leipzig: Reclam
      Books volume 89
    - Darwin, Charles. Die Entstehung der Arten Durch Naturauslese Oder Die Erhaltung der Begünstigten Rassen Im Kampf Ums Dasein.
      Books volume 29
    - Fajans, Kasimir. Über Die Stereochemische Spezifizität der Katalysatoren
      Books volume 39
    - Planck, Max. Acht Vorlesungen Über Theoretische Physik. Leipzig
      Books volume 188
    - Einstein, Albert. The Meaning of Relativity. London
      Books volume 34
    - Roth, Walter and Karl Scheel. Landolt-börnstein Physikalisch-Chemische Tabellen, Zweiter Erganzungsband II, Berlin: Verlag von Julius Springer
      Books volume 195
    - Findlay, Alexander, Max A. Bredig, and Alexander Findlay. Einführung in Die Phasenlehre Und Ihre Anwendungen
      Books volume 40
    - Drucker, C, and E Proskauer. Physikalisch-chemisches Taschenbuch Band II. Leipzig: Akad. Verl. -Ges
      Books volume 32
- Series IV: Photographic Materials, IV
  Series IV contains 279 images that document the environment in which Georg Bredig worked. It includes many portraits of Bredig's colleagues and family members, as well as images of the laboratory settings where Bredig was employed.
  - Framed Photograph of Georg Bredig, circa 1930
    Graphic Materials box 23 object 1
  - Framed Photograph of J.H. van't Hoff and Wilhelm Ostwald in the Ostwald Laboratory in Leipzig
    Graphic Materials box 25 object 1
  - Oversized photographs: Eleven oversized photographs, including group portraits from conferences, circa 1894-1922
    Graphic Materials box 26 object 1-11
  - Postcards - Sixty-four postcards, containing both images and correspondence. Includes both portraits of individuals and laboratory settings in Germany. Includes images of Robert Bunsen, Louis Pasteur, et al.
    Graphic Materials box 22 object 1-64
  - Framed Photograph of J.H. van't Hoff, circa 1890
    Graphic Materials box 24 object 1
  - Photographs - 101 photographs, including portraits of Bredig and his colleagues, laboratory settings in Leipzig and Heidelberg, as well as scientific buildings in Europe. Includes images of Wilhelm Ostwald, Svante Arrhenius, Ernst Cohen et al.
    Graphic Materials box 21 object 1-101
- Series V: Works of Art, V
  Series V contains works of art including a framed painting of a seascape by Wilhelm Ostwald. The painting was gifted to Bredig by Ostwald's widow for Christmas in 1933. Also in this series is an etching of Fritz Haber by Emil Orlik, which was dedicated to Georg Bredig and autographed by Fritz Haber in 1928.
  - Framed Etching - Etching of Fritz Haber by Emil Orlik. Dedicated to Georg Bredig and autographed by Fritz Haber
    Graphic Materials box 28 object 1
  - Framed Print - Robert Bunsen, undated
    Graphic Materials box 28 object 2
  - Framed Painting - Seascape painted by Wilhelm Ostwald in Tenerife, Spain, 1913. Gifted to Georg Bredig by Helene Ostwald in 1933
    Graphic Materials box 27 object 1
- Series VI: Artifacts, VI
  Series VI contains an assortment of small artifacts belonging to either Max or Georg Bredig. It includes two mortar and pestle sets, custom stamps, an empty glass vial and a manual drafting set.
  - Mortar and Pestle (white)
    Realia box 29 object 3-4
  - Unidentified wooden container with small metal cup inside. Stamped "G. Bredig"
    Realia box 30 object 3
  - Custom Monogram Stamp "A.F."
    Realia box 30 object 7
  - Metal plaque depicting Wilhelm Ostwald
    Realia box 29 object 1
  - Mortar (white)
    Realia box 30 object 1
  - Manual drafting set
    Realia box 29 object 2
  - Custom Monogram Stamp "G. Bredig"
    Realia box 30 object 6
  - Glass vial with cork stopper
    Realia box 30 object 2
  - Mortar and Pestle (dark grey)
    Realia box 29 object 5-6
  - Printers Block Stamp depicting the Bredig Arc Method for the preparation of colloidal solutions.
    Realia box 30 object 4
  - Custom Monogram Stamp "M. Bredig"
    Realia box 30 object 5
Science; Physics; Physical inorganic chemistry; Nazis; Jews -- Migrations; Jews -- Persecutions; Jewish Science; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Colloids; Chemistry, Physical and theoretical; Chemistry
Waals, J. D. van der (Johannes Diderik), 1837-1923; Urey, Harold Clayton, 1893-1981; Svedberg, Theodor, 1884-1971; Solvay, Ernest, 1838-1922; Schnell, Eva; Schnell, Alfred; Rutherford, Ernest, 1871-1937; Planck, Max, 1858-1947; Ostwald, Wilhelm, 1853-1932; Nernst, Walther, 1864-1941; Mark, H. F. (Herman Francis), 1895-1992; Kuhn, Richard, 1900-1967; Homburger, Viktor; Homburger, Marianne; Hoff, J. H. van 't (Jacobus Henricus), 1852-1911; Haber, Fritz, 1868-1934; Ehrlich, Paul, 1854-1915; Cohen, Ernst, 1869-1944; Bohr, Niels, 1885-1962; Bodenstein, Max, 1871-1942; Berl, Ernst, 1877-1946; Arrhenius, Svante, 1859-1927
Photographs; Books; Art; Archival materials
Vanadium Corporation of America; University of Michigan; Universität Leipzig (1409-1953); Universität Heidelberg; Technische Hochschule Karlsruhe; Princeton University; Oak Ridge National Laboratory; Max-Planck-Gesellschaft zur Förderung der Wissenschaften. Fritz-Haber-Institut; Gurs (Concentration camp); Eidgenössische Technische Hochschule Zürich